<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Country-mans physician where is shew'd by a most plain and easie manner, how those that live for from cities, or market towns, and cannot have the advice of physicians, may be able of themselves, by the help of this book, to cure most diseases happening to the body of man : a work very useful and necessary for all that understand not the learned languages.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34751</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16999393</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16999393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105682</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34751)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1612:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Country-mans physician where is shew'd by a most plain and easie manner, how those that live for from cities, or market towns, and cannot have the advice of physicians, may be able of themselves, by the help of this book, to cure most diseases happening to the body of man : a work very useful and necessary for all that understand not the learned languages.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine, Popular.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105682:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105682:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COUNTRY-MANS Phyſician. WHERE Is ſhew'd by a moſt plain and eaſie manner, how thoſe that live far from Cities, or Market Towns, and cannot have the advice of Phyſicians, may be able of themſelves, by the help of this Book, to Cure moſt Diſeaſes happening to the Body of Man. A Work very uſeful and neceſſary for all that underſtand not the Learned Languages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwel,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105682:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105682:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>I Am not Ignorant, that there are ſeveral Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Phyſick, alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Publiſhed in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue: but truly they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all of them ſo ſtuft, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with hard terms of Art, and difficult Deſcriptions and Definitions, or the Receipts, (the chief thing deſign'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb facs="tcp:105682:3"/> for the Buyer) all in the <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue; that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not at all perceive any, or very little difference from their being continued in the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Languages they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in; ſo that they muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be ſomething of Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to underſtand thoſe Books, and ſo of little or no uſe to thoſe that are none: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon taking the Premiſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſerious Conſideration, I thought I ſhould do a very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable piece of Service to my dear Country-folks, that underſtand no more than their Mother-Tongue; if I ſhould write a very plain method for them, whereby they might be
<pb facs="tcp:105682:3"/> able by the help thereof to Counſel and Adminiſter to themſelves, and their friends, and neighbours, fitting and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Remedies for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Curable Diſeaſes, when and where they cannot conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently have the advice of the Learned Phyſician or Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, living perhaps remote from any Market Town, or City where ſuch commonly inhabit. For the Book it ſelf, I can ſay that, as the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is, good Wine needs no Buſh; ſo I am confident thou wilt find it will be able to commend it ſelf, it being a choice Collection of almoſt infallible experiments from the
<pb facs="tcp:105682:4"/> moſt Famous Printed Authors, and curious Manuſcripts; and I have (for the Reaſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpecified) made it ſo plain and eaſie, that any though no Scholars, nor at all vers'd in the Learned Languages, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre in following theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in this Book.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:105682:4"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE <hi>DISEASES</hi> &amp; <hi>CURES,</hi> Treated of in this BOOK.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. OF the Diſeaſes of the Head, whether cauſed from Heat or Cold, where likewiſe of the inveterate pain of the Head, <hi>Page</hi> 1.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:105682:5"/>
               <item>CHAP. II. Of the Diſeaſes and Pains of the Eyes; where of the Chataract. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</item>
               <item>CHAP. III. Of the Diſeaſes of the Noſe, as ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers thereof; where of the bleeding at the Noſe. <hi>p.</hi> 13.</item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. Of the Diſeaſes of the Ears, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Wormes, noiſe in the Ears, and Deafneſs; where alſo how to Cure the Pain in the Ears. <hi>p.</hi> 19.</item>
               <item>CHAP. V. Of the Diſeaſes of the Mouth, as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers thereof; where of a ſtinking breath; of too much and too little ſpitting; likewiſe of the Diſeaſes
<pb facs="tcp:105682:5"/> and Pains of the Teeth, and of the Cure of the Quinſey. <hi>p.</hi> 22.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VI. Of the Diſeaſes of the Breaſt, as the <hi>Coughs ſhortneſs</hi> of <hi>Breath, Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of <hi>Blood,</hi> and of the Ptyſick. <hi>p.</hi> 27.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. Of the Diſeaſes of the <hi>Side,</hi> as the <hi>Pluriſie,</hi> and of the Pains of the Side. <hi>p.</hi> 33.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VIII. Of the Diſeaſes of the <hi>Heart,</hi> as the feebleneſs thereof, and the beating of the Heart, and ſwooning away. <hi>p.</hi> 35.</item>
               <item>CHAP. IX. Of the Diſeaſes of the <hi>Stomack,</hi> and firſt
<pb facs="tcp:105682:6"/> of the weakneſs thereof, whether from a hot or cold cauſe, of nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating meats, and loſs of taſte, and appetite; where of the Wind in the Stomack, whether before or after eating, and of the Hiccop. Of ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vomiting, whether from an hot or a cold cauſe, and of provoking Vomit if there be occaſion, and to comfort the Stomack, after Vomiting, and laſtly of the pains of the Stomack. <hi>p.</hi> 37.</item>
               <item>CHAP. X. Of the Diſeaſes of the <hi>Belly,</hi> and firſt of the Diſeaſes of the <hi>Liver,</hi> whether from hot or cold cauſes, <hi>viz.</hi> from Choler or Phlegm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where of its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. 2. Of the <hi>Spleen,</hi> of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes; where of its obſtruction like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and alſo of the Cure of the three ſorts of Jaundies; that is, yellow, green and Black. 3. Of the Cholick and Iliac paſſions. 4. Of the pain in the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, and difference between that and the Colick; as alſo of the Cure
<pb facs="tcp:105682:6"/> of their Gravel and Stone, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the Cure of the Stone in the Bladder, and difficulty and heat in voiding of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine. 5. Of the Cure of the Three ſorts of Flux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the Belly, <hi>viz. Lientery, Diarrhaea,</hi> and <hi>Diſſentery.</hi> 6. Of the Dropſie and Wind, and Grip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Belly. 7. Of the both ſorts of Hemorrhoids, <hi>viz.</hi> inward and outward. <hi>p.</hi> 42.</item>
               <item>CHAP. XI. Of the Diſeaſes belonging to Women, as of the ſtopping and provoking their Monthly Courſes, and of the Curing of the Fits of the Mother, as alſo of the falling down of the Womb: Of their Barrenneſs like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and of how to prevent miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage, and how to cauſe eaſie Delivery of Women in Child-birth, and to eaſe their Pains after Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel; and laſtly how to cauſe plenty
<pb facs="tcp:105682:7"/> and ſcarcity of Milk in Women that give Suck. <hi>p.</hi> 52.</item>
               <item>CHAP. XII. Of breeding of Wormes and Teeth in Children. <hi>p.</hi> 59.</item>
               <item>CHAP. XIII. Of the Cure of Feavers, whether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Quotidian, Tertian, or Quartane. <hi>p.</hi> 61.</item>
               <item>CHAP. XIV. Of the Cure of the Peſtilence, and its Symptoms. <hi>p,</hi> 64.</item>
               <item>CHAP. XV. Of the Cure of the Gout, whether in the Hands, or Feet, or Knees, or Hipps. <hi>p.</hi> 66.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:105682:7"/>
               <item>CHAP. XVI. Of the Cure of outward pains in any part of the Body. <hi>p.</hi> 68.</item>
               <item>CHAP. XVII. Of the Cure of bruiſes in any part of the Body. <hi>p.</hi> 70.</item>
               <item>CHAP. XVIII. Of the Cure of Green Wounds and old <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers in any part of the Body. <hi>p.</hi> 71.</item>
               <item>CHAP. XIX. Of the Cure of all ſorts of ſwellings in any part of the Body, whether they be hot or cold, hard or foft. <hi>p.</hi> 78.</item>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105682:8"/>
               <p>by exceſſive heat or cold; and often from the infirmities of other Members, in which is contained the Cauſe of the pain in the head; as the <hi>Stomach,</hi> the <hi>Kidneys, Liver, Spleen, Womb,</hi> &amp;c. Now the pain is greater in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head than elſewhere when it proceeds from <hi>Blood;</hi> behind when from <hi>Flegm;</hi> when from <hi>Choler,</hi> the pain is moſt on the right ſide the head, and on the left when from <hi>Melancholy,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Medicines are to be imploy'd to the purpoſe, by oppoſing hot Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies to the cold, as <hi>Flegm and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy,</hi> and cold to the hot Cauſes; as <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Choler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The manner to cure the pain from a hot Cauſe, is firſt to let Blood in the Arm; then to apply Linnen Cloaths dipt in <hi>Plantain</hi> and <hi>Roſe Water,</hi> and <hi>Vineger,</hi> or in the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Lettice</hi> with <hi>Roſe-water</hi> and <hi>Vineger:</hi> Or Oil of <hi>Roſes</hi> and <hi>Poppies,</hi> and make a Pultis of <hi>Bole-Armenac</hi> white of Eggs a Roaſted Apple and Vineager, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105682:8"/> apply it to the head and forehead and temples, and waſh the head with warm water wherein have been boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Sage Leaves, Roſes and water Lilly-Flowers; and waſh the feet with the ſame, if he have no motion of the rheum; or a Bag of Roſes dipt in Roſe-water: or Cloaths dipt in the whites of Eggs, very well beaten with Roſe-water. Let them drink Cichory, Endive, Purſlain-waters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> mixt together, or one alone; or Barly-water with a little Liquorice Boil'd in it. And to the intent that your Remedies may be the more Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial, you muſt keep the Belly looſe by Gliſters, or Suppoſitories, or looſening Medicines, as Syrups of Violets and Roſes of each half an ounce, or ſo; or <hi>Caſſia, Lenitive Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary,</hi> or <hi>Diaprunes,</hi> or <hi>Catholicon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For a cold <hi>cauſe</hi> apply to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and jaws, wild Time, or Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain, or Rue, ſteept or dipt in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger and Honey of Roſes; or To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105682:9"/> or Mint; or water-Creſſes, or rub the head with Aſarabac-leaves, or the Juice of Melilot mixt with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger and Oil of Roſes. To drink wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherein Betony hath been boil'd; applying the Leaves to the Temples. To ſnuff up into the Noſe the juice of ſow-Bread, or Gith ſteept in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, and Powder of Pellitory of the Wall to make Sneeze: and make a Bag with hot Herbs and Flowers, as Melilot, Sage, Betony, Roſema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; of white Snakeweed; the ſaid Herbs and Flowers having been Perfum'd with the Vapors of Betony and Balm, put upon a Plate of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, or hot; and caſt thereon Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger and Roſe-water: Perfume likewiſe the head with dry things, as Roſes and Maſtich; or with Red-Roſes and Salt, but it muſt be when the ſpitting comes not; for then for (fear of ſtopping the breath) you muſt be content to Perfume the head Cloaths only, applying them hot to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105682:9"/> the head; and if the pain ceaſes not by theſe Remedies then uſe hotter things, as Bags made of Marjoram, Rue, Bays, Juniper-Berries; or a fomentation of the decoction of the ſaid things; or elſe anoint the head with Oil of Camomile and Dill, one or both together; or Oil of Rue, Spike, Caſtor, adding to them a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Pepper, or Muſtard Poudred; to draw up into the Noſe, the Juice of Marjoram, or Fenel, is an Excellent Remedy; After the Application of theſe Remedies before ſpoken of, you muſt make a Cap of Taffaty doubled, lined with Cotton, which you ſhall ſtuff with Flowers of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram, Camomile, Red-Roſes, Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, Cinamon, Nutmeg, Cloves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> finely Poudred: and if there be a Catarrh, uſe Mirtle Berries, Frank-incenſe, and the Gum of the Juniper Tree.</p>
               <p>The Inveterate pain of the head is cured by Roaſting a piece of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105682:10"/> outer pill of an Onion under the Cindres, and ſteeping it in Oil of Bays and Roſes, and put into the Ear where the pain of the Head is; Bleeding and Purging firſt; and you muſt alwayes keep a Temperate diet without which all is in vain. Eat no windy nor ſalt Meats; be quiet in his mind, not Write, nor Read, but bear patiently his pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the Diſeaſes of the Eyes.</head>
               <p>FOr the Diſeaſes of the Eyes you muſt purge the Brain, foraſmuch as the greater part of the inward Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes proceed from the Brain, diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling its ſuperfluous and malignant Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors upon them, or the lower parts furniſhing with Cauſes, whereby the ſight is diminiſhed and the Eye pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and this is the Phyſicians buſineſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105682:10"/> to diſcern the particular Humors that cauſe the Diſeaſes; and to evacuate them by proper Purgations, as Pills, Glyſters, Potions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for what concerns the outward means you muſt keep the Head dry and clean, rubbing it well behind every morning, by that means diverting the Humors which fall from the Brain upon the Eyes; it makes much like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the preſervation of the ſight to keep the Feet dry, moderately hot, and not moiſt; 'tis likewiſe good for the ſame purpoſe not to ſleep in the day, nor hold the Head much down; to be bound in the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is bad for the ſight, wherefore you muſt keep it ſoluble, you muſt ſhun the Wind, the Cold, Heat, too much looking upon the Sun, and much Light, or great Fire; much Reading and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Weeping, to Sleep or Wake much. As to Eating and Drinking, you muſt Eat Meats of good nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not Windy, Salt, nor Spicy,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105682:11"/> little or no ſtrong Drink. The uſe of Eye-bright is very good againſt all maladies of the Eyes, Boiled in Pottage, or Drink the Pouder, or Boil it in the Drink?</p>
               <p>The <hi>Film</hi> or <hi>Cataract</hi> is Cured by the Pouder of Sugar-Candy, Tutty, white Coperas, mixt equal parts and ſearc'd, and put into the Eye, Night and Morning; the Pouder alone of white Beans hath the ſame Property. To this end ſerves likewiſe a Water made of half an Ounce of Tutty, a quarter of an Ounce of Mace, Pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Infuſed in white Wine and Roſe-water of each half a Pint; put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in a Glaſs and let them ſtand in the Sun, in Summer, about a Month, keeping it from Rain and Dew; ſhaking the Glaſs often.</p>
               <p>Another for the ſame purpoſe; Take a couple of new laid Eggs, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted hard under the Cinders, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their ſhells, cut them in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and take away the Yelk, and fill
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105682:11"/> up the place with Sugar-candy and Tutty equal parts, then joyning them together with a thread, ſteep them in Roſe-water, in a little Veſſel: when they have ſtood twenty four Hours, Strein and Preſs them through a Linnen Cloath; of which Liquor drop a few drops into the Eye Night and Morning.</p>
               <p>The Diſtilled Water of theſe things following cures the <hi>Cataract</hi> likewiſe; Plantain, and little and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pomegranate flowers, red Roſes, ſprigs of Fenel, of each an handful, crums of white Bread, hot out of the Oven, one Pound, mix them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſteep them ſix hours in white Wine, then Diſtill them.</p>
               <p>To the ſame purpoſe Diſtill this Water.</p>
               <p>Take of Fenel, Rue, Verben, Eye-bright, Endive, Betony, red-Roſes, Venus-hair, equal parts, ſteeping them before twenty four Hours in white Wine, the Liver of a Buck, three
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105682:12"/> Ounces, Diſtill them thrice in <hi>Balneo Mariae;</hi> and the laſt Water will be very proper for Cataracts, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maladies of the Eye, preſerving the ſight to Old Age.</p>
               <p>Another very Excellent one. Take Snails and Diſtill them in <hi>Balneo Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae,</hi> waſhing them well firſt; and in eight Ounces of their Water infuſe one of Tutty prepar'd, Sugar-candy, white Dung of a Lizard, dryed Bones, two Drams of each, red Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Aloes, Sal Armoniac, of each one Dram; being all well Poudred and put into the Water, muſt be put into an Alimbec, and the Water that comes from them ſerves Effectually as before, and alſo to clear the Eyes of all ſpots, and Redneſs; preſerving the ſight ſo well and ſo long, that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent People have ſeen as well as if they had been but 30.</p>
               <p>This Unguent following is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good for the Eyes, Curing their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation and Redneſs, ſtaying the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105682:12"/> ſharp Defluxions which make them Blear-Ey'd, Annointing them Night and Morning.</p>
               <p>Take half an Ounce of Tutty fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Poudred in a Bel-metal Morter, then Grind it on a Marble with Roſe-Water, as Painters do, then dry it in the Sun; then Grind it again, with freſh Roſe-water; do thus ſeven or eight times, then mix it with the ſame weight of freſh Butter; and your Ointment is made.</p>
               <p>Another ſingular Unguent for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Eyes is thus made.</p>
               <p>Take two Ounces of freſh Porks Greaſe, ſteep it in Roſe-water ſix Hours, then waſh it again twelve times in the beſt white-Wine, for the ſpace of five or ſix Hours; then add to this Greaſe Tutty well prepar'd, and very finely Poudred one Ounce, <hi>Lapis Haematites</hi> well waſht, one ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Aloes well waſht and Poudred twelve Grains, Pearles Poudred three Grains, Incorporate them all well
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105682:13"/> together with Fenel Water, and make an Unguent, whereof put a little into the corners of the Eyes.</p>
               <p>The laſt Remedies to divert the importunate Humor from falling from the Brain upon the Eyes, are <hi>Caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and <hi>Setons;</hi> which muſt be done by the Surgeon by adviſe of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, or you may try Bliſters drawn behind the Neck, or behind the Ear; make them with Leaven, Pigeons Dung, Spaniſh-flies, and Brandy, mixt well together.</p>
               <p>Now to Cure the pain of the Eyes and redneſs that follows come from a blow; Apply a rotten Apple there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; the Blood drawn from the Wing of a Pidgeon: Alſo the Decoction of Fenel, Camomile, and Melilot made with Water and white-Wine; Applyed with Linnen Cloaths. But above all other Remedies, Agrimony alone, as hath been Authorized by often Experience, rubb'd between the Hands, and put upon the Eye
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105682:13"/> hurt; and roul it on, Cures it in a ſhort time, though very red with bruiſed Blood and the ſight darkned, it brings it again: For want of the Herb take the Water Diſtilled in the ſeaſon of the year. To abate the redneſs of the Eyes, the firſt time that you drink every Day, it muſt be a full Glaſs of clear Water, and ſo continue till you be Well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the Diſeaſes of the Noſe.</head>
               <p>THe Diſeaſes of the Noſe are divers likewiſe, inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as for the inward you muſt alwayes remove the Cauſe, by the Advice of a Learned Phyſician; and for the outward employ theſe Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies following.</p>
               <p>The ill ſcent of the Noſe is Cured by waſhing it with a Decoction made
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105682:14"/> of white-Wine, Ginger, Penny-Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, Cloves, Calamus Aromaticus, of each equal parts, and after put Pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Pellitory into the Noſe or drawing up the Noſe often, Wine wherein Nutmeg hath been ſteeped four Hours; or Anointing the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills Night and Morning, with Oleum Nardinum; wherein have been Boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Clove-Gilliflowers, wood of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes, with a little Musk; or with this Compoſition, or elſe to make Tents thereof, and put them in the Noſe, to wit, Ginger, dryed Roſes, wood of Aloes, of each two Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Myrrh, Calamus Aromaticus, of each one Dram, mix them well with good Wine, and reduce them to a Paſte; adding thereto ſix Grains of Musk, and make Pills of the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Pea, dipping it in Oil of Nard when you uſe it.</p>
               <p>The Noſe being ſtopt by ſome Humor that hinders Breathing, is opened with Juices of Beets and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105682:14"/> incorporated in Oil of bitter Almonds, and drawn up the Noſe; alſo by the ſmoke of Tobacco only taken at Mouth, and make it go out at the Noſe.</p>
               <p>To provoke ſneezing, blow up the Noſe, Pouder of Pepper, Pellitory, and Orris Roots, or mix the Pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with ſome Liquor, and anoint the Noſtrils therewith.</p>
               <p>To ſtay the ſneezing ſcratch the Soles of the Feet and Palms of the Hands; rub the Eyes and Ears; ſmell to white Lilly, and Bath your hands in warm Water.</p>
               <p>To Cure the Ulcers and Itchings of the Noſe, take the Juice of Ivy, and ſour Pome-granates mixt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; alſo the Anointment made of Ceruſs, Aſhes of wake Robin, and Honey of Roſes. The Phlegm that runs from the Noſe like Snot is ſtay'd by proper Remedies for the Cure of the Brain, whereby the Spring of ſuch Noiſome Humors is dryed. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105682:15"/> then to this end Frictions, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, Caps, as before; and beſide, uſe ſome proper Syrup to correct the ill ſcent of the Snot's abundance, and thinneſs; as Syrup of Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, Diacodium, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo to this purpoſe you muſt hold in your mouth little Pills made of Bole-Armenac, Terra-Sigillata, Amber, Dragons Blood, Cloves and Musk.</p>
               <p>The Blood flowing diſorderly from the Noſe is ſtopt by a Frontal made of the Pouder of Sanderac, made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Paſte with the whites of Eggs, and applyed with a Linnen Cloath; by the Juice of Onions, mixt with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, put into the Noſtrils with Cotton, by drinking Mint Water, by Anointing the forehead with an Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made of Dragons Blood, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtich, Frankincenſe, and whites of Eggs; by Camphor mingled with the Seeds of dead Nettles, Juice of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and Houſe-Leek put into the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, by Pouder of red Coral, or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105682:15"/> Terra Sigillata drank; by Bathing the palms of the Hands and ſoles of the Feet with Cloaths dipt in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Roſes, and Plantain water; by Bathing a mans Stones and a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Breaſt with Fountain or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon water; this is of great efficacy according to experience: You may ſtay the Bleeding at Noſe alſo by putting to the nuque of the Neck a Bag wherein is Toads Pouder; which muſt be made of a great Toad, that is Bred upon the Earth, not the Water; the which you muſt put in an Earthen Pot alive, and put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Oven with Bread, and then Pouder it. And the ſame Pouder will ſerve in the Bloody-flux, or Womens Fluxes, and to ſtay the Bleeding of Wounds, applying it to the oppoſite of the hurt part. The like Virtue hath the Seed of Flix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weed, Poudred and taken a Dram thereof, either in Wine, or with an Egg, or Broth; it ſerves alſo to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105682:16"/> looſen the Belly, and to make great Bellyed Women gayly bear their Burthen. But contrarywiſe the Herb Millefoil put into the Noſe provokes Bleeding, it being ſometimes neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for diſcharge of the Brain. But this by thruſting it in the Noſe, the point formoſt: for the contrary hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens if you put the Stem firſt in.</p>
               <p>The Smelling corrupted, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt loſt, is regained by the often handling and ſmelling of Mint, alſo a Perfume made of the Leaves of Southernwood, Rue, Juniper, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling Gith-ſeed therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105682:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. Of the Diſeaſes of the Ears.</head>
               <p>FOr the pain in the Ear, put into it ſome drops of Oil of Roſes, and Vineger, or the juice of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane; beſides it will be convenient to apply thereto a Bag ſtuft with Camomile, and Melilot Flowers: the juice of dwarf Elder and Rue is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good; making the inward part of the Ear firſt clear from filth. The water of Honey Diſtill'd; Milk with a little Saffron. The like Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue hath the Perfume of the Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Camomile, Dill, and <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas,</hi> made in Water wherein hath been put warm Vineger, wherein burnt Nitre, and Sal-gemm have been diſſolved, put in the Ear with a Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105682:17"/>
               <p>The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> of the Ear are Cured by Inſtilling Oil wherein have been boiled white Leeks, and Earth Worms, to the Conſumption of the third part, or by the Oil of Eggs alone.</p>
               <p>Againſt the Wormes in the Ears the Milk of the Fig-tree and the figs alone are very proper; alſo the juice of Capers, of Wormwood, Calamint, Centaury, Germander, juice of the Peels of Walnuts, or the Bark of the Tree; alone or together.</p>
               <p>Againſt the noiſe in the Ears pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from wind or other Cauſes, 'tis good to put into the Ear a tent dipt in Oil of Rue, Caſtor, or Spike, with juice of Leeks; alſo in a Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſting, 'tis very healthful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Vapor by a Funnel putting into the Ear, water wherein hath long boiled, Marjoram, wild Mint, Sage, Camomile flowers, Aniſeeds, and Fenelſeeds, and a Coloquintida Apple, and to the end the Vapor pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105682:17"/> the further, let the Patient have ſome hard thing between his Teeth, as Peaſe or Beans, chewing them with force; the ſame will be good at Night going to Bed; and having received it put in the Ear one drop of Oil of Coloquintida, then ſtop the Ear with Cotten dipt in the ſaid Oil, and lye down there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
               <p>Deafneſs is cured by means of an Unguent made of two Ounces of Gooſe-greaſe melted with a gentle fire, and two drams of Aloes Socco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine in Pouder incorporated, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Cotton, putting it into the Ear; or the juice of Radiſhes mixed with Oil of Roſes; or with the fat of an Eel and Oil of bitter Almonds, or the juice of an Onion, mixed with Honey, or by the Pouder of Aloes diſſolv'd in white wine, Inſtill'd warm into the Ear, and after make him ſneeze with ſome Pouder of Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, or by the fume of the wood of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105682:18"/> Oak which you may do by lighting a ſtick at one end, and putting the other into the hollow of the Ear, but you muſt have a branch of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one of one years growth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knots.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Of the Diſeaſes of the Mouth.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> of the Mouth are Cured by waſhing the Mouth with a Decoction of the Herbs of Mouſeear, Conſound and Golden Rod; or Pomegranate flowers, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, Plantain, Agrimony and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, adding a little Alum towards the end, or with Wine wherein have Boil'd Aniſeeds and Cloves; or with the Diſtill'd water of Scolopendrium; or with Treacle water, and the like quantity of Roſe-Vineger, and Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, wherein hath been diſſolved a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105682:18"/> little Bole-Armenac; or with Honey of Roſes, by rubbing the Ulcerate places of the Palate or the Tongue. The Decoction of the Herb Speed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, in Wine, gargariz'd dryes the Ulcers of the Mouth, and waſh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in fevers: And for a ſingular Remedy touch the Ulcer with a drop of Oil of Vitriol.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Super abundance</hi> of Spittle is corrected by uſing aſtringent and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gargariſms, made by boiling Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Pomegranate flowers, Plantain and Alum in Water and Wine; 'tis alſo good to Eat Biſquet, and dry Roſted meats, and Muſtard; to eat Cubebs and green Ginger: On the contrary to provoke Spitting; chew Sage, or Maſtick, or Tobacco, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or at other times.</p>
               <p>For the Curing a <hi>Stinking Breath,</hi> from what Cauſe ſoever, waſh the Mouth with Vineger of Squils, or a Decoction of Mint, Balm, Fenel and Aniſeed; chew Nutmeg, Cloves, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105682:19"/> Root: hold in the Mouth a Pill made as followeth; Gum-dragon one Ounce, Dragons Blood two drams, ſteep them in Roſe-water for two dayes, then put them in a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Morter with ſix drams of Sugar, three of Cinamon, five of Starch, a ſcruple of Musk; all diſſolv'd in Roſe-water, mixt together with a Peſtle; after it is dry make Pills to hold in the Mouth. To take away the ſmell of Onions or Garlick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> chew Cloves, Aniſeeds, Fenelſeeds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or waſh the Mouth with Roſe-water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Diſeaſes of the Teeth ſpring from divers cauſes, hot and cold; if from cold do as followeth, waſh them with one of theſe Decoctions; Wormwood boil'd in ſtrong Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the Leaves of Ivy in red Wine, with Lavender, Sage and Marjoram; Cypreſs Leaves and Nuts, and Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-Berries, Roſes, Mirtle Leaves in white-Wine, Oil of Cloves, Sage
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105682:19"/> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are good dipt in Lint or Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton to put into the Tooth if hollow. If the pain proceed from a hot cauſe, then apply the Oil of Poppy, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drake, Henbane, or their Decoctions in Wine; or Henbane root boil'd in Roſe-water and Vineger; or hold Vineger in your Mouth wherein hath been boiled Camphor. And from what cauſe ſoever the pain proceeds it will be appeaſ'd by the Oil of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baneſeed; made after this manner. Beſprinkle Henbaneſeed with Brandy, then put it in a Glaſs Viol, which ſtop very well, and make this boil in a Pot of water twenty four hours, then take off the Phiol, and pour out the Seeds, while it is yet hot, put them in a Cloath, and ſtrain them with a Preſs, and ſo your Oil is made. Hold Milfoil-root between your Teeth, or Pellitory, or Agrimony, or chew Maſtick incorporated with new Wax.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105682:20"/>
               <p>To preſerve the Teeth, waſh your Mouth every Morning in fair water, if they be looſe rub them with this Pouder, Compos'd of Myrrh, Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Alum burnt, Pumice ſtone burnt, all in equal parts apart; finely Pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and mixt. Crums of Bread with Salt, after Eating to rub with, and then waſh them with fair water and a little Vineger, or red-Wine, Perles, both Corals, Ivory, Cryſtal, white Marble, Alabaſter, Cubebs, Harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn, Maſtick, dryed Bones, Tartar, white Copporas, Sal-gemm, Crabs Eyes, Eggs-ſhels, Snails-ſhels, Oi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters-ſhels, dry'd Roſes, Orris, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maris, Spikenard, Dragons-blood, Venice-hair, Pomegranate-flowers, Sumach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all Poudred apart, and mixt.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Quincey,</hi> 'tis good to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle the Mouth with water of Speed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well diſtill'd in <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> or its Flower boiled in Vineger and Honey, or Mint, Sage, Rue, and Coriander,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105682:20"/> boil'd in Cows or Sheeps Milk; or the Decoction of Figs and Cinquefoil in Water, diſſolves the Tumor, or the aſhes of a Swallows Neſt burnt with the young ones, made into a Pultis, with Oil of Camomile and ſweet Almonds is excellent: Peach-Gum boil'd in Vineger, with a little Saffron, or a Liniment made of Bores Teeth Poudred with Linſeed Oil, or to drink a dram of the Pouder in <hi>Carduus Benedictus</hi> water: Here you muſt ſend for a Chyrurgion and the firſt thing you do let Blood, it may be, more than once.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Of the Diſeaſes of the Breaſt.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, when one ſpeaks low and with pain, take at Night going to Bed two Ounces of Wine where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in have boil'd, Figs and Raiſins, with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105682:21"/> Sugar, Cloves and Cinamon, and the Tablets of <hi>Diarios</hi> given Morning and Evening clears the Voice; and Syrup of Iujubs. So doth the deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Enula Campana,</hi> or <hi>Oximel</hi> wherein Liquorice hath been boil'd. For a Sovereign Remedy is this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor taken at Night going to Bed; put an Ounce of Pouder'd Sugar in a Porringer, and pour thereon as much Brandy as will cover it, or a little more; put it upon the Coals, then light your Brandy with a Paper, lighting as often as it goes out, till it will take fire no more, then let the Patient take it all at once.</p>
               <p>To Cure a <hi>Cough,</hi> the Remedies before are good, but eſpecially theſe, boil in water, Raiſins and Figs, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, Aniſe and Fenel-ſeed till the third part be waſted, and of this give Night and Morning, two hours before meals 2 or 3 ſpoonfuls after eating a Tablet of <hi>Diaireos,</hi> or <hi>Diapenidion,</hi> or take Night and Morning a ſpoonful of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-Candy
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105682:21"/> Poudred, and as much of Diaireos, and a quarter of an Ounce of Liquorice, and drink three Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Hyſop or Scabious water after. Or Syrup of Liquorice and Hyſop taken Night and Morning with Pti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſane, adding a few Aniſe and Fenel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, and Nettle Seeds; when the Cough preſſes, 'tis good to take Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels confected with Sugar, Conſerve of Roſes, and taking often one or other, or <hi>Lohoc Sanans,</hi> or <hi>de Pino</hi> taken with a Liquorice ſtick, ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them by little and little, or take two or three hours in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before Eating, the juice of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, boil'd half away with Honey or Sugar, ſweating after it, or an Ounce of this drink two or three hours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Eating; take <hi>Caſſia</hi> newly drawn, two Ounces and an half, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acarthamus</hi> ſix drams, new Penids and <hi>Diaireos ſimplex,</hi> of each half an Ounce, Conſerve of Violets three Ounces, ſweet Almonds and Liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105682:22"/> Pouder, of each half an Ounce, Syrup of Violets two Ounces; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve theſe in Pullit Broth; and you muſt remember that you muſt Eat no ſharp, or ſalt things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt ſhortneſs of Breath call'd <hi>Aſthma,</hi> theſe Remedies are good beſides thoſe for the <hi>Cough;</hi> a Lohoc made of an Ounce of Raiſins ſtoned, two great Figs, one Date, dryed Hyſop, Venus hair, Liquorice, Fox Lungs prepar'd, Scabious water of each one dram, Penids two Ounces, and Syrup of Liquorice as much as will thicken it; the which take with a Liquorice ſtick, two or three hours before or after meats. And as the Aſth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſurpaſſes the <hi>Cough</hi> in malice, ſo you muſt be more obſervant in your diet; Eating not Sharp, or Salt, or Spices, but Eating Barly boil'd in Almond Milk and Sugar, Eating Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and Pidgeons, and roſted Fowls; Figgs and Raiſins, Dates, Almonds.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105682:22"/>
               <p>Againſt <hi>Spitting Blood,</hi> give the Pouder of red Coral in Diſtill'd wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the tops of Oak; or <hi>Terra ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillata,</hi> with Plantain or Knotgraſs water. Ambar in the Decoction of Conſound. Harts and Goats horn in one of the Waters.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Ptiſick,</hi> let the ſick drink every Morning four hours before Eating, two or three quarts of Aſſes Milk, or red Cows, newly drawn, putting in each time a Spoonful of Sugar of Roſes in Pouder. Taking often Conſerve or Sugar of Roſes, or <hi>Diatragacanth,</hi> 'tis good to drink each Morning faſting, a good Glaſs of this Diſtillation, of the Herb aſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoof; the great Conſound, Venus hair, Hyſop, equal parts with Snails diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd of their ſhels, and well waſht. The water if alone is as good, and for all lean and dry Bodies, uſe Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blets made of two Ounces of Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernel in Pouder and Sugar, every Morning, diſſolv'd in three Ounces
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105682:23"/> of Pimpernel water. This Pouder is very ſalutary, taken two drams in the Morning, and two Spoonfuls of Syrup of Jujubs after it; or Colts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot water, or Ptiſane. Take three Drams and a half of each of the four cold ſeeds which are Gourges, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truls, Melons, Cucumers, and as much of Quince ſeeds, five drams of white Pepper ſeeds, Juice of Liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, Hyſop, Starch, Gum-Arabick, Diatragacanth, of each one Dram and an half, Penids the weight of them all, Pouder all apart then min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105682:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. Of the Diſeaſes of the Sides.</head>
               <p>THe moſt dangerous of all is the <hi>Pleuriſy,</hi> and moſt difficult to Cure, for it will ſoon kill if not ſoon cur'd. To know it, the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent hath a burning Fever, a great Cough and ſhort Breath, and a great pain in his ſide, by reaſon of fiery Blood hath inflam'd the membrane that covers the Rib inwardly, which is mighty ſenſible; now without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay let him be let Blood on the ſame ſide; and give to drink a dram of Bores tooth prepar'd with ſome Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral Syrup, as Violets, Coltsfoot, Hyſop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If he find no abatement and full of Blood, Bleed again. Then give this, Take three Ounces of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus water, a Spoonful of white-Wine, ſix ſperms of new lay'd Eggs,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105682:24"/> a dram of Bores-tooth, a ſcruple of red Coral Poudred, give all together warm.</p>
               <p>To open the Apoſteme if there be occaſion, take an Apple cut in two and the Kernels taken out, fill it with Frankincenſe, or Maſtich, tye it with a Thred, Roſt it under the Cinders, and give it to Eat, and to void the matter, Drink of the decoction of red Poppies, or a dram Poudred; with Scabius, and Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernel water, and Syrup of Hyſop; if the Fever be not great, elſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olets.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:105682:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Of the diſeaſes of the Heart.</head>
               <p>FOr theſe your Remedies muſt be according to the cauſes; the weakneſs of the Heart coming from heat, give every Morning ſome Wine and water and Sugar, with <hi>Troches</hi> of <hi>Camphire,</hi> one dram; or <hi>Diamarga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riton Frigidum;</hi> and Eat often Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of Borage, Bugloſs, Violets, alone, or with water of Wood-ſorrel. If the cauſe be cold, with ſadneſs and fear, take every Morning, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary call'd <hi>Diamoſch,</hi> one dram in good Wine, and keep his Breaſt warm; and once a week take a dram of <hi>Venice Treacle,</hi> in Wine; or half a dram of <hi>Confectio Alchermes,</hi> and to have Cloves and Mace and Nutmeg boil'd in his drink and diet. For the beating of the Heart, adviſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105682:25"/> with the Phyſician about Bleeding and Purging, if he have a Fever drink Syrup of Limons, Violets, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, with Roſe or Borage, or Bugloſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, or the Syrup with Purſlain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'tis good to ſmell oft of Roſes, Violets, and Roſe Vineger; if without Fever give <hi>Aqua-Mirabilis, Caeleſtis,</hi> or ſo, or good Wine, let him ſmell to Benizon, Storax, Musk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Swounding,</hi> firſt of all throw cold water in the Face, tie the Legs, Arms and Thighs very hard, and rub them hard, pull by the Hair; then give Wine to drink, and hold Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to his Noſe. But if from the Womb, let her ſmell ſtinking things, as <hi>Aſſa Faetida, Caſtor,</hi> Partridge Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers burnt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and contrarily Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes below with <hi>Benzoin, Storax,</hi> Musk, Ambar, Civet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but if it come from loſs of Blood, ſweating, Flux, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then nothing like good Wine, and comfortable nouriſhment as Gellies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:105682:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. Of the Diſeaſes of the Stomach.</head>
               <p>WEakneſs of the Stomach pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds oft from Flegm deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Head like Rheum, and being cold Digeſts not meat, but with great difficulty; to that the firſt Remedy muſt be moderate abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, but if <hi>Pain</hi> preſs, you muſt Vomit, with an Ounce of <hi>Crocus Metallorum,</hi> if a woman, and never above ten drams to a man, and after drink Wine; or <hi>Hippocras, &amp;c.</hi> and ſometime Purge the Stomach with <hi>Pilulae Hierae cum Agarico,</hi> or <hi>Stoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicae cum gummi,</hi> and taking two or three Night and Morning; keep his Stomach warm with Cloaths or Emplaſters. If from an hot cauſe, they will be dry, and little appetite, Head-ach, ſowr Belchings and offers
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105682:26"/> to Vomit, then give Syrup of Roſes, Sorrel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or Quinces in Endive or Cichory water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Diſdaining</hi> of diet comes from too many Cholerick or groſs and clammy Phlegmatick humors, always dry, ſometimes Vomiting yellow Choler; firſt let Blood, and Purge the Choler with <hi>Diaprunes, Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, &amp;c.</hi> then give two or three ſpoonfuls in the Morning of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Wormwood or Mint in white Wine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Windineſs</hi> of the Stomach from the Mouth before eating comes from clammy Flegm, or wateriſh, to Purge with <hi>Extractum Rudij,</hi> two Scruples, and <hi>Pilulae Stomach. cum gummi</hi> one, mixt, take three Pills at Night, and three in the Morning, and you need not keep within doors if it be not extreme cold: then take for three or four Mornings two Spoonfulls of Syrup of Wormwood or Mint faſting.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:105682:26"/>
               <p>The <hi>Windineſs</hi> after eating comes from heat of the Stomach, and being weak cannot digeſt the meats; for this take Anniſe, Fenel, Cummin and Carway ſeeds Poudred with Sugar, or <hi>Aromaticum roſatum, Dianiſum,</hi> or <hi>Diacyminum,</hi> faſting, drinking a little Wine after, or two ounces of Wine wherein the ſeeds before have been boil'd; remembring alwayes to keep the Stomach warm as before, eat no raw fruits, or windy meats; and ſleep not in the day time.</p>
               <p>To Cure the <hi>Hiccup,</hi> hold the Breath as long as may be, ſleep long, ſneez, ſpit, ſtir, tell them ſad ſtories, and frighten them, it proceeds ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from fulneſs, ſo they muſt be moderate in diet; But if it come from weakneſs of the Stomach after long ſickneſs, or flux of Blood or Belly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you muſt nouriſh careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with Gellies, Eggs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Stomach Vomits ſometimes by the benefit of nature, eaſily, what
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105682:27"/> offends it; but when by its weakneſs, it cauſes violent motion, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient is in pain, as thoſe that have a little and ſtraight Stomach, long Neck and Breaſt, or weak ſight; you muſt then help nature by giving ſome warm water and Oil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> put your fingers, or feathers dipt in Oil as low as you can; on the contrary to ſtay <hi>exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Vomiting,</hi> cauſed from an hot weak <hi>Stomach,</hi> drink Syrup of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Quinces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with water well boil'd and cold; if from cold keep the Stomach warm as before, and let him Vomit with <hi>Crocus Metallorum,</hi> and ſee before.</p>
               <p>To comfort the <hi>Stomach</hi> after Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting give Syrup of Mint, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for all pains in the Stomach from any cauſe, take half a pint of Roſe water and a quartern of Brandy, an Ounce of Cinamon Poudred, with enough Sugar, let them ſteep ſix hours in the Liquors, and give it to drink. Great pains of the Stomach have been ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peas'd
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105682:27"/> by applying a great Cupping Glaſs upon the Navil, ſticking on an hour; and with hot bread dipt in Oil of Camomile applyed to the pain. Drink an hour before eating a glaſs of good Wine wherein hath ſteeped two drams of <hi>Diacyminum,</hi> or <hi>Dianyſum,</hi> or Maſtich in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Mints, with Aniſeed, or Cumin; or a little Caſtor in good Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:105682:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. Of the Diſeaſes of the Belly.</head>
               <p>THe humors which nouriſh the members of the Body are made by eating and drinking, and digeſted by the natural heat of the <hi>Liver,</hi> aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that of the Heart; but is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hindred to perform its Office through too much heat, with much pain coming upon the ſuperfluity of Blood and cholerick humor, or through diminiſhing of the natural heat, when flegm which is cold, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds. Red Urine, quick Pulſe, ſpittle ſweeter than ordinary ſhew Blood is the cauſe, if choler 'tis yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower and clearer than uſual; dry, and hotter than before, and leſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite; if Phlegm, the Urine that's whitiſh and thick cauſes a heavineſs about the Liver, the face is pale.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105682:28"/> Now for the Remedies; from Blood let Blood in the Arm, drink cool drinks, as Ptiſan, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> keep the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looſe by Clyſters, or gentle Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and abſtain from fleſh, but eat meats boil'd with fenel and purſlain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Almond Milk, Peaſe roſted or ſodden Apples, Prunes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler cool alſo, take a week together an Ounce of Syrup of Endive or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olets in Ptiſan, Morning and Night, or of Endive, Cichory or Sorril wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, each an Ounce, then take half an Ounce of <hi>Caſſiia</hi> new drawn, a dram of Rhubarb, infus'd all Night in Whey or Endive water, or an Ounce of Syrup of Violets, inſtead of <hi>Caſſia;</hi> or a Bolus of half an Ounce of <hi>Caſſia,</hi> as much Electuary of the Juice of Roſes, or a dram of Rhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb; or diſſolve it in Whey or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dive water. After he may take eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Morning two or three ſpoonfuls of this Iulep, half a pint of Roſe water, a quartern of Endive, five Ounces of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105682:29"/> Sugar, and to cool more, two Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Vineger; who hath the Liver cool'd by <hi>Phlegm,</hi> muſt for a week take faſting Oxymel compound with the Decoction of Parcely and Fenel, then Purge with an Ounce of <hi>Diaphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum,</hi> or <hi>Diacarthamum</hi> in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of the roots of Parcely and Fenel; he may drink ſtrong Ale or Bear, or Wine, and eat Spices; when the pain of the obſtruction of the Liver comes from the Stomach, 'tis cured by laxative medicines; and when 'tis accompanyed with pain of the Reins and Back by openers, as Syrup of Venus hair, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Parcely and Fenel Roots. Oft obſtructions come to Women by reaſon of ſtopping of their motnhs, then bleed them in the Arm firſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Foot if need; and take for a week opening decoctions as before, with as much white Wine, added.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spleen</hi> is the receptacle of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy and clearer of the Blood ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105682:29"/> one jocund, but if it be obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by too much melancholy, all the Body becomes dry, 'tis known by a pain in the left ſide after eating, and a blackiſh colour of the face, and ſadneſs; and cured by letting blood in the Arm and Haemeroid Veins; and if the pain be accompanied with drought, and loſs of taſt, it ſhews it proceeds from an hot cauſe, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides bleeding give cool things as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or decoction or Syrup of <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopendria</hi> and <hi>Endive;</hi> then Purge with half an Ounce of the Juice of Roſes, and three Ounces of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctions of the roots of Capers and <hi>Scholopendria;</hi> with Caſſia and Diaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenna of each half an Ounce.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Jaundies</hi> proceed from the Diſeaſes of the Liver and Spleen, and as their Diſeaſes are divers, ſo are the <hi>Jaundies,</hi> to wit, <hi>Yellow, Green,</hi> and <hi>Black,</hi> the laſt from the Spleen, the other from the Liver. For the Yellow and Green, drink in the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105682:30"/> Morning Syrup of Violets with Houſe leek water, or Syrup of Endive with Cichory water, then Purge Choler as before, in the Liver; let the ordinary drink be Ptiſan made with Barly, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quorice and Prunes, or Tamarinds; Earth worms waſh'd and Poudred and given in white Wine, is good: alſo the waters or decoction of Venus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hair, or Queen of the Medows; For the Black Jaundies, after all as before, clap a large Cupping glaſs to the Spleen, often Night and Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Colic</hi> is a Violent pain all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Belly, for which firſt drink a good draught of Scabious water with a little Treacle, then give a Clyſter made of Mallowes, Mercury, Violet leaves, with Aniſe and Caſſia, Hony and Salled Oil, and this often, and a Purger of Choler as before; when 'tis caus'd of wind it runs up and down, then give to drink Wine or Ale where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Aniſe and Fenel and Cumin Seeds
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105682:30"/> have been boil'd; or the water or decoction of Camomile, alſo the Pouder of old Acorns or Cheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts in white Wine.</p>
               <p>The pain of the <hi>Kidnies</hi> which comes from the Stone or Gravel is like the <hi>Colic,</hi> in that in both is Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, and binding in the Belly, and wind: but the Colic begins in the lower part of the right ſide go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the higher part of the left ſide of the belly, inclining more before than behind; but the Reins begin contrary, and the pain is ſtronger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore than after eating; the contrary in the Colic: and it commonly comes ſuddenly but the reins by degrees, with a pain of the back, and difficulty to make water: To cure which uſe open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things to void the ſtone, if little; for there are no Medicines in the world to break it; but firſt looſen the belly by an ounce of Caſſia, and Clyſters made with Mallows and Marſh-mallows and Beets, giving Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rups
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105682:31"/> and Decoctions thereof alſo at mouth; Turpentine Pills taken with White-wine, or the Decoction of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momil flowers in wine and water.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Difficulty of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine</hi> is cured by the ſame means; and <hi>Heat</hi> of Urine by a Bolus of an ounce of Caſſia, and a dram of Prunel and drinking cooling Emulſions of the four cold Seeds and Almonds with Barley water: and note that in all theſe diſtempers of the Reins, and almoſt in all other, the cure depends for the moſt part chiefly upon a good order of Diet.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fluxes</hi> of the Belly are three, whereof the moſt dangerous is called <hi>Lienteria,</hi> which is when meats are voided in the ſame ſort they were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at mouth, with very little al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, and without any ſtink; and <hi>Diarrhaea,</hi> when there is a Flux of flegmy and wateriſh humours only: Laſtly <hi>Diſſenteria,</hi> when blood is voided alone, or with excrements. For the firſt, you muſt quickly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105682:31"/> the Phyſician; in the mean time, let only comfortable things be given, with Syrup of Woormwood, Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, with Honey of Roſes, of each a ſpoonful, or diſſolved in Betony, Fenel, or Mugwort-water, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke vomiting by taking an ounce of Oxymel of Squils, and as much Syrup of Wormwood, or two ounces of Oxymel; then take Marmelad of Quinces before he eat, or <hi>Aromati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Roſatum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>Diarrhaea</hi> note it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time beneficial to nature, when it is without Fever, and quickly gone, and Bloody-flux not feared; ſo that you may let it alone for three or four days; then if you ſhall ſpie a few drops of blood threatning a Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, or the Patient be feveriſh, then give aſtringent Clyſters made of Sage, Mint, Borage, &amp;c. In the ſtrein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put ſome juice of the Shepherds purſe, or Bole-armenac, without any Sugar or Syrup, and in little quantities.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:105682:32"/>
               <p>For <hi>Diſſentery</hi> in the beginning let blood in the arm, and give lenitive Clyſters made of milk wherein ſteel hath been quenched; or with two or three yelks of eggs; give three or four a day; then purge with a dram of Rubarb, infus'd in Endive or Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chory-water ſtrein'd, and putting thereto half a dram of torrified Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb; then eat Marmalad of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Rice-milk, Sheeps and Calves feet, and Red wine alone, or with Steel-water.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dropſie</hi> is a moiſt ſwelling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in the feet, then the legs and thighs, then in the belly, and if neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected mounts to the heart: It is known by preſſing the part with your fingers, and if a mark remain it is the Dropſie, elſe not: For cure you muſt purge firſt, for which nothing is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than <hi>Jalap,</hi> a dram more or leſs in pouder with White-wine; then drink White-wine with Anniſeeds poudred; eat bisket and meats dry
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105682:32"/> roſted, drink as little as may be, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing all broths and fruits, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid meats; ſleep as little as may be, walk much, riſe early.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Gripes</hi> and <hi>Pains</hi> in the belly drink of the decoction of Mint, worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Camomile, Roots, Herbs and Flowers, in White-wine and water, or each alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here note for a general rule, that if you boil any things in white or other wine, you muſt infuſe them firſt over hot coals, letting them boil a walm or two firſt, and ſo ſtand, then boiling them very little again, ſtrein them out; for the wine loſes its virtue by boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>Hemorrhoids,</hi> they are inward, or outward; flowing or not. For the inward ſwelling apply a Cataplaſm of the white bread and milk, with two yelks of eggs, a little Safron, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Populeon:</hi> but above all other a Pultis made of <hi>Verbaſeum</hi> and <hi>Trifolium Hemorrhoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105682:33"/> with freſh Butter, whether they be inward or outward: If you will have them flow apply Horſe-leeches; and if they flow too much apply a Pultis of the white of an Egg and Bole-armenack, or burnt Paper, or Tinder, or pouder of red Coral a dram, in Plantan water or Red-wine inwardly; or the decoction of Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and Reſt-beef.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. Of the Diſeaſes belonging to Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</head>
               <p>TO provoke Womens Courſes drink a dram of yellow Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar poudred faſting, in White-wine: uſe moderate exerciſe; drink a dram of the pouder of the root of Dittany in the decoction of the herb, a dram of the Troches of Myrrh in White-wine:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105682:33"/> Theſe will do ordinarily, but if not, you muſt conſult the learned Phyſician: To ſtay their too much flowing, what I ſaid in Bloody-fluxes may be good here; or drink a dram of the troches of white Amber in Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan-water and Beer; You muſt not ſtir much, but ſleep much; rub the arms and ſhoulders well; apply Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-glaſſes to the dugs; eat little and often; keep the belly looſe.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Fits of the Mother,</hi> rub and tye the thighs and legs well; let her ſmell ſtinking things, Wooll, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridg feathers burnt, <hi>Aſſa ſoetida;</hi> but below ſweet perfumes of Civet, Roſes and Musk, &amp;c. Give her Mithridate to drink diſſolved in Wormwood-water or Peony-ſeeds poudred in White-wine.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Falling</hi> of the <hi>Womb,</hi> uſe contrary Remedies to cauſe it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to its place, to wit ſweet ſcents at noſe, &amp; ſtinking ones below for the Womb; and ſo quite contrary in all
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105682:34"/> the reſt. Vomiting is here requiſite; afterwards give pouder of Harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn or Bay-leaves to drink in Red-wine. But becauſe from the Womb proceed moſt diſeaſes in women, in any difficulty neglect not to adviſe with the learned Phyſician; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in caſe of</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barrenneſs</hi> of women in time of fertility, for conſervation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind under the benediction of God; and foraſmuch as their barrenneſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds for the moſt part from cold cauſes, we will begin with that, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſearch of other cauſes both of men and women to the Phyſician. After ſhe hath been well purged, the Womb muſt be fomented and perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the decoction of Mugwort, Wormwood, Savin, &amp;c. the day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter take Electuar, Aaromatick, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, and Sugar of each one dram; or take night end morning in good wine a Tablet of the pouders of Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, roots of Biſtort, Nutmeg, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105682:34"/> together with Sugar diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd in Balm-water.</p>
               <p>The women accuſtomed to <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry</hi> ought to uſe often the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves of Orange and Sage-flowers, Marmelade of Quinces, Dates, &amp;c. As ſoon as ſhe perceives the leaſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of miſcarrying, apply to her navil a hot loaf new out of the oven out in the middle, dipt in Malaga wine, and ſprinkled with pouder of Cloves and Nutmegs, and bind it cloſe on; apply to the loins this Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Maſtick two ounces, <hi>Labda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> three drams, Biſtort root, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons blood, Bole-armonack, Goats<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn burnt, of each half a dram, <hi>Terra ſigillata</hi> one dram, Frankincenſe, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Storax, Gum-arabick, of each one dram and half; Red Coral two ſcruples, Wax waſh'd in Roſe-water, and Turpentine two ounces: beat all in a Mortar with a hot Peſtle, pouring on oil of Myrrh and Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, ſtirring it ſtill with a hot Peſtle
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105682:35"/> till it be thick enough, then ſpread it upon leather, and apply it to the reins and loins. You muſt take off the Plaiſter every day, and waſh the loins and reins with equal portions of Roſe-water and White-wine, and lay it on again.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Delivery</hi> being come, and it be with difficulty, give her preſently a drink made of two ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of fine Cinamon, Wood-caſſia Bark, Troches of Myrrh of each one ſcruple, round Birthwort root half a ſcruple, <hi>Confectio Alchermes</hi> half a dram, ſyrup of Mugwort an ounce, Waters of Mugwort and Motherwort of each two ounces; or the decoction of Mugwort, Rue, and Dittany; or the juice of Parcely drawn with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar or White-wine: Hypocras is good, or the decoction of Harts-horn and Ivory: It is good to make her ſneeze, with fine pouder of Pellitory of <hi>Spain,</hi> and Tobacco, Oris, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Pains</hi> after Travel, the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105682:35"/> Oil of ſweet Almonds is very good to prevent them, and being come is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by diſtilled water of Peach flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; or this pouder in White-wine, roots of great Conſound, Nutmeg and Ambar, finely poudred, with a little Ambergris added.</p>
               <p>Too much milk ſometimes troubles them newly deliver'd, for which a Pultis of the great Celendine, Rue, Mint, Fenel, boild in water and vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, will be good: If the dugs be inflam'd anoint them with oil of Poppies, or Henbane, and the next day apply a Pultis made only of Bean meal and Vinegar, anointing the dugs and parts about with an Ointment made of an ounce of Bole-armenac, Biſtort root as much, with oil of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Myrrh, and Vinegar. This Pultis is very proper, made of two ſmall handfuls of dried Mint, one of Wormwood, boiled a good while, then add Bean, Lupines, and Orobe meal of each one ounce, with oil of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105682:36"/> Lillies. If the blood be clotted diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it by this Pultis; take four ounces of Smallage, Oxymel ſimple two ounces, Red chices meal two ounces, as much of Lupins: If it will not diſſolve, and that the kernels of the dugs are hard, and tend to ripen, take Marſh-mallow and white Lilly roots of each four ounces, twenty figs, boil them till they be ſoft, then add freſh Porks greaſe, or Butter enough for a Pultis.</p>
               <p>Now if you would procure a great quantity of milk, boil Barley and a little Fenel-ſeed in her broth, or Poſſet-drink.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:105682:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. Of breeding of Worms and Teeth in Children.</head>
               <p>AS in the diſeaſes of Women the Womb is for the moſt part concerned, ſo are Worms in Children the greateſt enemy; wherefore 'tis good in all their diſeaſes to add ſome Medicine contrary to the vermin: ſo that it is to uſe Children betimes to take Medicines, to the end they may the more eaſily be cured of their diſeaſes; then you muſt not wait till the worms be grown, but prevent them by giving them every new Moon ſome Wormſeed in a Fig, or Honey, or Treacle, or pap of an Apple; the Juice of Orange is good with its Rind poudred, giving one or other apart with a ſpoonful of Salad-oil. Syrup
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105682:37"/> of Limons kills the worms; ſo doth Harts-horn poudred mith Sugar; Mint poudred with Wine; Corian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſeed with the Juice of Limons or Pomegranates: but Rubarb is very effectual given in fine pouder in Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious water; or to little Children a ſcruple in Milk, or a little Honey of Roſes. The great worms that are voided by Children, dryed and pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred are excellent to drive out the ſame, drank in milk, wine or broth. Outward applications ſerve much to this effect; ſuch are Wormwood bruiſed and fryed and applyed to the ſtomach, and mole of the head. Here note that Syrup of Cichory with Rubarb is not only excellent in this caſe, but in all other diſeaſes of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants. Children are apt to vomit, for which let them wear upon their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach an Emplaſter of Maſtick thus made; ſpread ſome Virgins wax up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on leather, and in the middle make a hole, wherein put melted Maſtick.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:105682:37"/>
               <p>For Teeth rub them with Butter and Honey, &amp;c. if nothing will do, open the gums with a Groat or Lancet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. Of Fevers.</head>
               <p>HItherto of Remedies for certain particular diſeaſes; now for thoſe proper againſt <hi>Fevers</hi> that afflict the whole body. For the cure of a <hi>Continued Fever</hi> let blood if you can preſently, then eat very little, and drink Ptiſan or ſmall Beer, giving cool Clyſters, as you may ſee before; to abate great drought waſh his mouth with Vinegar and Roſe-water, and chew Sorrel leaves, or drink the juice.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Quotidian Fever</hi> is combated with before the fit with the Juices of Betony and Plantan mixt, or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105682:38"/> of Cinquefoil, Scolopendria, Middle bark of Elder, Betony leaves, roots of Smallage, Parcely, Raddiſh, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Tertian Fever</hi> the Proverb is found true, <hi>Ill luck is good for ſomething;</hi> two or three fits thereof being good to purge the body of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous humours in the Spring, but more are prejudicial; and dangerous in the Autum, for fear it turn to a Quartane: You may loſe your Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Fever by theſe Remedies, Take the Bark of a young Walnut-tree, that next to the wood; bruiſe it in a Mortar, and ſteep it in White-wine eight or ten hours, ſtrein it and drink it oft; this is for ſtrong bodies. Likewiſe ſteep in White-wine, Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, and Monks-Rubarb; give it when the fit's upon them. The juice of Plantan, Purcelan, Pimpernel are good apart: And in all Fevers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it is a chief matter to let blood, and keep the body looſe by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105682:38"/> gentle Purges or Clyſters, &amp;c. as <hi>Catholicon,</hi> Lenitive Electuary, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prunes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Quartane Fever</hi> many things are given, but few to purpoſe; theſe following are found good from experience; The ſeeds of Dwarf-Elder, one dram finely poudred for weak bodies, a dram and a half for ſtrong ones, and half a dram for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſteeped an hour in White-wine or Claret, and given when the fit ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; or dried Nutmeg upon the hot pan and poudred, half a dram given every morning; but on the Fit day in White-wine; or bind Pidgeons cut in two to the ſoles of the feet. In this Fever you muſt not drink water but wine, with very little water or ſtrong drink.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:105682:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. Of the Peſtilence.</head>
               <p>IN time of ſuch miſerable calamity two things are to be done, to wit to preſerve ones ſelf as much as may be from the diſeaſe, and to ſeek, under God, for a cure, if poſſeſt therewith. The moſt aſſured way of preſervation is not to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the infected, but dwell in a ſound place, the air cold and dry, rather than moiſt and hot; and to remember the commands of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, <hi>citò, longè, tardè;</hi> that is, to go quickly from the place infected, and to go a long way to a healthful place, from whence to be ſlow in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning till all danger be paſt: But if they muſt remain in an infected place, then to prevent, if poſſible, the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105682:39"/> Diſeaſe; you muſt Bleed and Purge, and Sweat, and keep all things ſweet and clean, and good Diet; keep Fires by night if in Summer, and all day in Winter; burn Frankincenſe and Benjoin, and Storax; never go out faſting. Take <hi>Pill. Ruffi,</hi> 3 or 4 or 6 Pills going to Bed, for cure and prevention; and <hi>Mitridates</hi> his Remedy compoſed only of one Figg and Walnuts, and Rue ſix Leaves, and a little Salt beaten together: comfortable Wines, and Waters, and Brandy are good, having a care there be not a great Feaver; then you muſt give Juice, or Syrrup of Lemmons with Barley-water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in Bleeding, you muſt have a care not to Let Women Blood in their laſt Moneth, or newly Delivered, or weak and decrepid Folks, or thoſe that have Swellings: In lieu of Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be uſed Cupping-glaſſes to the Shoulders and Thighs; after Bleeding give <hi>Caſſia</hi> or <hi>Manna</hi> the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105682:40"/> next day: Now for outward appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations you muſt here uſe no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percuſſive Medicines: After Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apply to the Bunch a Pultis made of Figgs, Raiſins ſtoned, and Leven beaten together with Oyl of Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil, or Bread and Milk, and Lilly Roots boiled together, or <hi>Diachilum cum Gummi,</hi> or <hi>Paracelſus</hi> Plaiſter, or <hi>Ammoniacum,</hi> or <hi>Galbanum,</hi> and open the Apoſteme before it be quite ripe; then dreſs it with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum Baſilicum</hi> with Tents from firſt to laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. Of the Gout.</head>
               <p>FOr the <hi>Gout,</hi> whether in the Hands or Feet, or Knees, or Hips, the chief remedy is to Let blood in a hot cauſe more than once if occaſion be, &amp; purge gently as you have been taught be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105682:40"/> if they be Feaveriſh, and give Clyſters, and then cool drinks as in Fevers, then uſe Ointments to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the pain; and Cataplaſms, and Plaiſters, and Oyl of Roſes and Lillies, &amp; a Pultis of Whitebread and Milk, and Oyl of Roſes; and to boil Hemlock and Henbane in Milk, and make a Pultis with Whitebread and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Populeon, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Anodynum,</hi> and bathe with Milk and warm Water, and apply <hi>Diapal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> Plaiſter ſoftned with Oyl of Lillies or Roſes; and <hi>Emplaſtrum de Ranis;</hi> or if from a cold cauſe uſe <hi>Paracelſus</hi> Plaiſter, and <hi>Oxycroceum, Diachylon cum gummi, cicuta,</hi> &amp; Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Plaiſters of Tobacco are excellent in all <hi>Gouts</hi> and <hi>Sciatica's,</hi> ſo is Oyl of <hi>Exeter,</hi> and Oyl of <hi>Spike</hi> and <hi>Turpentine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:105682:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI. Of the Cure of outward pains in any part of the Body.</head>
               <p>FOr pain o'th Members the Oyl of Dwarf-elder is very proper, anointing the place firſt therewith, if it be from a cold cauſe, and then apply hot Emplaiſters, as <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, &amp;c.</hi> as before in the Gout. Alſo Brandy and freſh Butter, or Pork<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe, never forgetting if the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent have need to Let blood i'th Arm, more than once if there be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and to purge gently two or three times together; as you have been taught before ſufficiently if you be ingenious. The Oyl of Elder-flowers, and Earth Worms mixt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether are excellent good, and this following; take Pitch and Roſin,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105682:41"/> new Wax, of each half an Ounce, freſh Butter half a Pound; melt them gently over the Fire in an Earthen Glazed Veſſel, all but the Rozin, which is to be caſt in, in ſmall pieces when the other have boiled a little, or begin to boil; then ſtir them well with a Wooden ſtick to incorporate them; with this compoſition being warm anoint your parts pained, and rub them as long as they can endure it, then lay an Emplaiſter of the ſame thereon, and ſo roul it up, if it be in a place that may be rouled; after it hath lain on twenty four hours, take the Plaiſter off, and anoint and rub it again, and lay it on again, and do ſo every twenty four hours till they be well. The Ointment and Plaiſter of Tobacco hath done great good to many.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:105682:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII. Of Bruiſes in any part of the Body.</head>
               <p>FOr Bruiſes, whether from blows, or falls, or any other cauſe, theſe remedies following are very good: Lupine-meal boil'd a little in Wine to the conſiſtence of a Pultis; Bean-meal boil'd in Vinegar, Radiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es beat with Hony takes away the marks of the Bruiſe. The leaves of Conſound mixt with Oyl of Saint-Johns-worth, diſſolves the clotted Blood in any part of the Body that comes from Bruiſes. This Oyl fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing is excellent good for all Bruiſes, and ſhrunk Sinews alſo. Take a young fat Fox, take off his Skin, then open him, and take ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Garbage, then boil him who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:105682:42"/> in common Oyl with Bay-berries, and Sage-leaves, and Marſh-mallow-roots till the Fleſh part from the Bones; and after you have broke the Bones put them into the Veſſel again, to boil the Marrow out, and let them boil a little, then preſs all hard out and keep it in Earthen Glazed Veſſels for your uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. Of green Wounds and old Sores.</head>
               <p>FOr Wounds from what cauſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you have ſeveral cheating <hi>Mountebanks</hi> that go up and down the Country, promiſing you Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Cures by their Balſomes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth. But if the Wound be of any moment, you'll find them moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly deceive you, and ſo you have work made for the Chirurgion, and that which perhaps if at firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:105682:43"/> handled, might with eaſe have been Cured, becomes it may be deſperate, or difficult, with hazard of Life or Limb: So that I thought good to give you this caution, and withal to give you the moſt approved way of Curing green Wounds, and Ulcers, and old Sores.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Then if any one happen to be wounded, be ſure to have in a readineſs always i'th houſe, that moſt incomparable Balſom called by the name of <hi>Linimentum Arcei,</hi> to be had at the Apothecaries, and if the wound be not hallow, ſpread ſome of it upon Lint, and apply to the wound, and bind it up; but if it be hollow, you muſt melt it in a Spoon, and pour it warm into the wound, or diſſolve ſome in Oyl of Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and pour it in, or inject it in with a Syringe, or you may make this Sovereign Balſome your ſelf, thus.</p>
               <p>Take Gum Elemi and Turpentine,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:105682:43"/> of each an Ounce and a half, Rams Suet old and tried two Ounces, old Hogs Fat tried one Ounce; the manner of making this Liniment is this, diſſolve the Gum in Sack, and let the Sack cimmer away gently o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the fire, then put in the Fats, and laſtly the Turpentine.</p>
               <p>Others make great eſteem of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco in the Cure of green Wounds and old Sores; either boiling the Leaves, or Juice alone thereof in Wine and Oyl, or by adding Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, Wax, and Gum, and Roſin; and ſo making Balſoms, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guents, and Emplaiſters thereof for the ſaid uſe; as for example, take this Receipt from the Colledge of Phyſicians of <hi>London,</hi> of an Unguent of Tobacco.</p>
               <p>Take two pound of the Leaves of Tobacco bruiſed, let them ſteep all night in Red Wine, and in the morning boil them with a pound of Pork Greaſe till the Wine be waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:105682:44"/> then ſtrein it, and add to the ſtreining half a pound of the Juice of Tobacco, Roſin four Ounces; then boil them again to the waſting of the moiſture, and towards the end ſprinkle in, of the roots of round Birthwort poudered finely, two Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and as much Wax as will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to make it of the conſiſtence of an Unguent. Or this way.</p>
               <p>Take four pound of the Juice of Tobacco, and boil it in a Skillet or Glazed Pipkin, with half a pound of Oyl-Olive till the Juice be waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; then put thereto of Roſin and Bees-wax, of each half a pound; when they are melted and mixt together, take them off the fire, and ſtir them continually with an Iron Spathula, and adding thereto half a pound of <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine, put them again over the Coals, and ſtir them very well together; laſtly take them off the fire, and pour them into a Glazed Earthen Veſſel, and let it ſtand till it
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:105682:44"/> be cold, then ſtop it and cover it cloſe, and keep it for the uſes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; this will laſt for many years.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another Balſome of Tobacco.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the Leaves of Tobacco, as many as you can hold between your two Hands, clean them well with a Linnen Cloth Leaf by Leaf without waſhing them, beat them in a Marble Mortar, with a Wooden Peſtle, then ſtrein the Juice through a Linnen Cloth, the which put into a Poſnet or Glaz'd Pipkin, with Roſin and Burgundy Pitch, of each a quarter of a pound, half a pound of Bees<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wax, as much freſh Porks Greaſe: all theſe mixt together ſhall be put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a gentle fire, for about the ſpace of an hour, skimming it alway with a Scummer, or till it be boild e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, which you will know by dropping a little upon a Board, and if it be of the conſiſtence of boiled Honey it is enough; then take it off the fire, and add thereto four Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:105682:45"/> or half a pound of <hi>Venice</hi> Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, then mix it over the fire, and ſo pour it out as before. Or thus,</p>
               <p>Take three Ounces of new Bees<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wax, and as much Roſin, melt them in a Poſnet or Pipkin, as before, over a Charcole-fire; when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to boil, throw in a pound and a half of the Juice of Tobacco, boil them altogether over a gentle fire, for five or ſix hours, in which time the moiſture will be conſumed, then ſtrain it through a ſtrong Linnen Cloth, and put it into the Pipkin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, adding thereto half a pound of Turpentine, mix them over the fire, and ſo keep them for your uſe as before: The ſimple Balſome of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco may be made this way,</p>
               <p>Take what quantity of Leaves of Tobacco you will, bruiſe them as before, and put the Juice into a thick Glaſs Bottle, with as much Oyl of Olives, and put the Glaſs well ſtopt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:105682:45"/> into Horſe-dung, and deep covered for forty days, at the end take it out, and you will find a Balſome ſwimming o'th top, the which pour very gently off from the dreggs, and keep it in a Glaſs for your uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Compoſitions of Tobacco, are likewiſe good for Bruiſes and old <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and cold Tumours,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Another excellent Balſome: Put into a glazed Earthen Veffel, Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone finely Poudred and Salted, pouring thereon as much Oyl as will ſwim above the Brimſtone four fingers breadth; put them i'th Sun and let them ſtand till they be thick, by ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them once or twice every day, then pour off the cleareſt for your uſe.</p>
               <p>Another excellent Oyntment for green wounds: Take an Ounce of <hi>Oleum Petroleum,</hi> half an Ounce of <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine, and as much Oyl of Olives, two drams of Maſtich; mix them all together, and boil them
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:105682:46"/> over a gentle fire, till they come to the conſiſtence of an Oyntment or Balſome; and keep it in an Earthen Glazed Veſſel cloſe ſtopt for your uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX. Of Swellings and Apoſtumes.</head>
               <p>FOr any new Swelling, apply pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently a Pultis made only of the Crums of White-bread, boil'd in Milk, and when it is boil'd to the thickneſs of a Pultis, add ſome Oyl of Roſes, or freſh Porks Greaſe, or freſh Butter thereto: or Marſh-mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and white Lilly-roots, and Figs boil'd in Water with Oyl, freſh Butter, or Pork Greaſe as before, will break it if it muſt be broken. Alſo Bean and Barly-meal boil'd in Hony and Water, diſſolves Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and brings them to Ripeneſs.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:105682:46"/> The Leaves of wild Clary, ſteept in Vinegar, and applyed with Hony reſolves Apoſtumes. If theſe do not you muſt Adviſe with the expert Chirurgeon, and remember always to roul the part ſwell'd with Linnen Roulers.</p>
               <p>Thoſe kind of Apoſtumes we call Felons, may be ripened and ſoftned by theſe means following: Take Wheat-flower, and Pork Greaſe, Hony, and the Yelk of an Egg, mix them hot over the fire, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the Felon. Or this, take Bean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meal, Leven, Figgs, Raiſons ſton'd, mix them together as before, and apply it; or Plantan Leaves beaten in a Mortar with Oyl of white Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and apply'd thereto; or Sheeps Dung ſteept and mixt with Vinegar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To conclude this Chapter, I will give you the Receipt of a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Plaiſter of Tobacco, againſt all kinds of Cold and hard Swellings what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and to heal old <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:105682:47"/>
               <p>Take half a Pound of the Juice of Tobacco, of the Juice of Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood three Ounces, Oyl of St. <hi>Johns</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worts ſimple, Oyl of Elder, of each an Ounce and a half, of the Leaves of Wormwood, Conſound, and Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort of each one handful, White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine a quarter of a Pint: Let the green herbs boil in the Juices, and Wine and Oyls in a Poſnet, ſtirring them continually with a wooden Spathula to the bottom, that they burn not to; but let them not boil till they be too thick and no moiſture left; then taking them and ſtreining them hard with your hands or a Preſs, diſſolve in that Liquor you ſtreined, four Ounces of Bees-wax, and two Ounces of Bucks Greaſe or Suet; then take it off the fire, and Incorporate therein two Ounces of <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine, Frankincenſe, Maſtick and Myrrh, of each one Ounce, finely Poudred apart, and ſo when 'tis cold enough, make it
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:105682:47"/> up into rowls of plaſter, to be ſpread upon leather when you have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX. Of Burnings and Scaldings.</head>
               <p>FOr any kind of Burning or Scald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whether directly by Fire or boiling Water, or Oils, Pitch, Fats, or ſcalding Lead, or Gun-powder, &amp;c. theſe Remedies following you will find to be profitable, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the purpoſe: Firſt of all you muſt ſee to take out the fire that is in the burnt part, as well to advance the cure, as to prevent bliſters and cruſts which may follow, without proper remedies, and indeed the marks of the burn that appear after the cure. Firſt then, as ſoon as 'tis burnt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint it with Salad-oil and Water beaten well together, and ſtrew
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:105682:48"/> thereon Wheat-flower; and dip Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen clothes or Flax Tow in the ſaid Oil and Water, and lay them on; or Roſe or common water with the whites of Eggs beaten to water, and oil of Roſes, or Lillies, or Poppies; or for all uſe Snow-water if you have it; and indeed you ſhould never be without it. If notwithſtanding all this through the malice of fire bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhall ariſe, you muſt then cut them with Ciſers, and lay thereon freſh butter boil'd, oil of Roſes and yelks of Eggs beaten together: The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Baſilicum</hi> will cure them perfectly, or this Unguent follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Take half a pound of freſh But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter well boil'd and ſtrein'd, Ceruſe and Tutty, waſhed both in Plantan or Roſe-water, of each half an ounce, burnt Lead a quarter of an ounce, with four yelks of Eggs, mix them all together to the form of an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent. A Pultis made of the leaves of Bur-dock with the whites of Eggs
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:105682:48"/> cures burns; alſo Hen-dung mixt well with hony of Roſes, or oil of Roſes: The decoction of Mallow leaves and freſh Butter beaten a great while together, and applied in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a Liniment, with a Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort leaf, a little warm, is good to ſeparate the burnt cruſts, if any: ſo are yelks of Eggs with oil of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets mixt together. To appeaſe the pain coming from burns, imply this Unguent; Take old Bacon greaſe melted in an earthen glazed Veſſel, and pour it into Roſe-water, then ſtrein it through a linnen Cloth, then waſh it five or ſix times in Plantan-water; to four ounces of Lard ſo prepar'd add two yelks of Eggs, and make them into an Ointment. The oil of the yelks of Eggs is ſingular to appeaſe the pains; and that the marks of the burn may not be ſeen after the cure, you muſt waſh the part often with Plantan water, with a little Allum diſſolved therein. To
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:105682:49"/> remove ſuch Cicatrices likewiſe a Liniment made of the herb call'd Porks bread, beaten with Houſleek is very proper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI. Of a Scald-head.</head>
               <p>THis is a loathſome diſeaſe, and requires skill to cure it well. Out of many ſound Experiments make uſe of theſe following: Take two handfuls of the herb Celandine, four ounces of Bay ſalt, and as much quick Brimſtone finely poudred; beat the herb well in a ſtone or wooden Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, with a wooden Peſtle; that done boil them in ſweet Oil altogether; then take them from the fire, and ſtrein them through a Linnen Cloth, to extract their ſubſtance; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with anoint the head of the Patient night and morning.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:105682:49"/>
               <p>Another Remedy. After having waſh'd the head with Beef Piſs, and rubbing it therewith till blood come almoſt, then lay on the pouder of Hens-dung dried in the Oven, and thereon an Emplaſter made of the Soot of a Furnace mingled with ſtrong White-wine Vinegar.</p>
               <p>Another is this. Take two ounces of common Turpentine well waſh'd firſt in common water, then in Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitary water, freſh. Butter one ounce waſh'd in Roſe-water, Bay-ſalt half an ounce, two Yelks of Eggs, the Juice of Limons and Oil of Roſes, of each one ounce, a ſcruple of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir, and mix them together, and make an Ointment.</p>
               <p>Another for the ſame is made of Roch-allum, Vitriol, and Verdigreeſe, and quick Brimſtone, Soot of a Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, of each three drams, Camphir two drams, Oil of ſweet Almonds, and Porks Marrow of each half an ounce; incorporate them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:105682:50"/> and make them into an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent. Sometimes it happens that we ſearch for that a great way off which is nigh at hand; and that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines of a ſmall price do as much good as dear Drugs; or as we ſay in the Engliſh Proverb, <hi>Far fought and dear bought is good for Ladies;</hi> as may be ſeen in this matter; for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper-berries boil'd in Vinegar and Honey, and apply'd in manner of a Pultis, is excellent good. In Infants it is much more eaſie to cure the Scald-head, than in thoſe of riper years; and in theſe more eaſie than in old folks, the time rendring it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable; wherefore it is very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to diſtinguiſh between age and age, and remedy and remedy, to go artificially to work; that is to ſay, for the young uſe gentle remedies, and to others ſtronger.</p>
               <p>Note here that in little children this Diſeaſe is commonly healthful, it delivering them from the Falling,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:105682:50"/> ſickneſs and Convulſions, and other fearful diſtempers, by purging them from the impure blood they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted in their Mothers womb.</p>
               <p>The difficult ſort of Scald-heads are diſtinguiſhed into dry ones and moiſt ones: For the dry one begin with this decoction: Take two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Fumitary, Monks-rubarb, and roots of Mallows, flowers of Meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot and Camomile, of each two ſmall handfuls, Linſeed, Beans and Lupines, of each a quarter of a pound; boil them in Lee made of the aſhes of a Vine-tree, or Fig-tree; bathe and waſh the head therewith twice a day, then anoint it with this Unguent fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: Take a pound of Lard, Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitary, Monks-rubarb, and Ivy, one handful, ſlice them very ſmall; then add two ounces of oil of Bays, four ounces of oil of Maſtick, half an ounce of Turpentine, four ounces of the juice of Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>orts; beat all theſe well together, and then let them ſteep
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:105682:51"/> twenty four hours, then let them boil till the juice be conſum'd; then ſtrein it, and anoint the head there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, laying on after a Colewort leaf.</p>
               <p>For the moiſt Scald-head waſh and bathe it with a decoction, as before, wherein you have diſſolv'd Roch-Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum; then anoint it with the Unguent call'd <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum de minio,</hi> to be had at the Apothecaries; then take Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degreeſe, with Allum, Honey, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, of each two ounces, a dram of Arſenic, two of Sublimate, all in pouder; boil them together till they begin to be thick enough for an Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and you will find this a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Ointment.</p>
               <p>Here you muſt remember to cut the hair cloſe, or ſhave it away firſt of all: ſome apply a Cap of pitch to tear it up by the roots.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:105682:51"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXII. For the Scabs and Itch in the hands.</head>
               <p>FOr theſe in the hands the water of a Smiths Forge to waſh and bathe the hands well in is good; or Allum-water, or the juice of Limons alone, the brine of ſalt Bacon, or brine of Pickle-herring, or Anchoves, the Lee made of Oak-aſhes: then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Nicotianum,</hi> or <hi>Enulatum cum Mercurio,</hi> or flower of Brimſtone mixt with either of them: and ſo if the whole body, letting blood firſt, and purging, uſe thoſe Ointments to anoint withal, uſing a temperate diet, and drinking as little ſtrong drink as may be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:105682:52"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIII. Of the Tetters and Ring-worms.</head>
               <p>THey are an unhandſom ſight, and therefore to quit your ſelf of them, note that againſt them are employ'd divers Remedies, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of them: thoſe that are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious may be cured with gentle and mild remedies, but the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and malignant with more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, by application of more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſtronger remedies, as in the Chapter before. For the not rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious do thus; waſh and bathe them in the decoction of Beans and Wheat in Vinegar: or take a thin ſlice of Veal, Beef, or Mutton, lay it upon the coals or Gridiron, then beat it with Vinegar and Muſtard, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:105682:52"/> this to the Tetter. Or take Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe, Oil of Roſes and Vinegar, and make an Ointment and anoint: Now if theſe will not do, being firſt applyed to rebellious ones, then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your ſelf to theſe following; Firſt waſh and bathe them with a decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Lupines and Marſh-mallow roots, made in Vinegar to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of half; or with Plantan-water wherein hath been infuſed white Vitriol and burnt Alum. Or make an Unguent of two drams of Aloes diſſolv'd in diſtill'd Vinegar. Oil of Wheat alone is excellent for this purpoſe; it is made by putting Wheat between two hot irons and the Oil will drop out; or elſe thus; Take ſome Wheat beaten and put it into a glaſs Veſſel, and ſtop it cloſe, and put it into a Kettle of water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the coals, to keep the water hot, and not to make it boil, and ſo let ſtand three days together; at the end thereof take out the pouder and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:105682:53"/> you will find it moiſt; the which put into a Linnen Cloth, and preſs the oil hard out.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV. Of Corns in the feet and toes.</head>
               <p>THeſe often hinder people from going in eaſe; and ſo ought to be conſidered, and to have remedies laid down for their help: for which are divers uſed, but theſe following may prove moſt effectual: ſome bathe and waſh them firſt in a Decoction of herbs, and then cut them with a ſharp Penknife, or Razor, as far as they can poſſibly go, then apply a Plaſter of ſoft Wax red or green, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been firſt ſteep'd 24 hours in ſtrong White-wine Vinegar; for the Cinabar and Verdigreeſe, wherewith theſe Waxes are coloured, will kill
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:105682:53"/> and take away the roots of the Corns. The ſame will theſe remedies follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing do effectually, ſometimes one, ſometimes another, according to their divers properties; of which you may chooſe which will be beſt for your purpoſe, and make uſe of them, <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banum</hi> and new wax mixt together; ſome take Lilly roots well boil'd, and then beaten with Porks marrow and apply it: ſome uſe onely <hi>Emplaſtrum de ranis cum mercurio.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXV. Of the Ruffneſs and Chops in the hands and lips.</head>
               <p>THe Chops in the hands and lips coming from cold winds, or other cauſes inward or outward, are cured by theſe Remedies following; having firſt waſhed them with Barly-water,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:105682:54"/> then anoint them with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum roſatum,</hi> or <hi>Pomatum</hi> at the Apothecaries, or Capons Greaſe, or Oil of Wax is excellent, for it will cure them in a ſhort time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI. Of Warts in any part of the body.</head>
               <p>THe juice of Limons kill Warts in any part of the body; or the ſame juice diſtill'd, or diſtill'd Vinegar; or the juice of the leaves and flowers of white Mullein: Oil of Vitriol &amp; Brimſtone are infallible, but you muſt uſe them warily: The juice of the ſtocks of Purſelain and Houſleek bruiſed in a Mortar with Bay-ſalt, and the Warts rub'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with often, cures them in three or four days.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105682:54"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105682:55"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105682:55"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
